Haema Nilakanta

Resume

⊠ nilak008@umn.edu

¹¹¹ Website: haemanilakanta.github.io
Last Updated: October 14, 2022

Summary Statement

Experienced data scientist with foundational training in statistics and an expertise in statistical computing and applied statistical methodology. Strong statistical programmer, presenter, individual and team contributor, and dedicated to diversity and inclusion within the larger data science field.

Skills

Programming R, Python, Spark (Pyspark and SparkR), SAS, Hadoop, Hive, Oozie, SQL, Shell, XML

Statistical and Regression, General Linear Models, General Additive Models, Mixed Methods, Hierarchical Modeling, Bayesian Machine Modeling, Regularization, Time Series, Survival Analysis, Experimental Design (A/B testing), Parametric and Non-parametric Methods, Cross Validation, Classification, NLP, Decision Trees, Random Forests, Boosting

methods & Bagging Methods, Neural Networks, Recommender Systems, Simulation-based Approaches

Operating Mac, Windows, Linux

Systems

Other Tools Git, LaTeX, Microsoft Office, Keynote, Pages

Other Confident public speaker, strong communication skills, adaptable

Education

March 2020 PhD, Statistics, University of Minnesota, Twin Cities, Minneapolis, MN.,

Advisor: Prof. Galin Jones.

Dissertation: Output Analysis of Monte Carlo Methods with Applications to Networks and Functional Approximation

Feb 2018 Master of Science, Statistics, University of Minnesota, Twin Cities, Minneapolis, MN.

2012–2014 Graduate coursework, Biostatistics, The George Washington University, Washington D.C.

May 2011 Bachelor of Science, Magna Cum Laude, Mathematics, Iowa State University, Ames, IA.

Relevant Experience

Present Principal Data Scientist, Target Corporation, Minneapolis, MN.

- Working with Target Tech Data Science Pricing and Promotions Insights
- Director-level individual contributor and technical leader in developing models and algorithms that improve business planning and operations
- o Part of a larger team that oversees development and deployment of pricing and merchandising models at Target
- Mentorship of fellow data scientists
- o Collaboration and coordination with other Target teams

Oct 2019-22 Lead Data/Al Scientist, Target Corporation, Minneapolis, MN.

- o Worked with Target Tech Data Science Personalization Deals team to drive deal-based recommendations at scale
- o Senior member and contributor, maintained and upgraded production workflows, code reviews, and innovation
- o Reliable onboarding and technical mentor
- o Developed, deployed, and managed recommendation systems and prediction-based models
- o Collaborated and coordinated with other Target teams (e.g., promotions, pricing, Circle, etc.)
- Key Projects (used Hive, Python, Pyspark, SparkR, Shell, Oozie):
- 1. Generalized fallback: Led development of a productionized daily-run algorithm from scratch to generate non-personalized ranking of all offer types at Target (GLMs, seasonality, random forest)
- 2. Personalized recommendations of price based offers: Led development of a productionized daily-run algorithm from scratch to generate personalized recommendations of price based offers to all identifiable guests (xgboost)
- 3. Eligible Items: Collaborated on a real-time recommendation service to rerank items within an offer for guest relevancy (under patent review; word2vec, cosine similarity)

2019-2018 Graduate Instructor, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN.

- Spring 2019 STAT 3032-001: Regression and Correlated Data
- o Fall 2018 STAT 3011-017: Introduction to Statistical Analysis
- o Fall 2018 STAT 3701: Introduction to Statistical Computing (covered initial 6 weeks)

Summer 2018 Data Science Graduate Intern, Target Corporation, Minneapolis, MN.

- o 10 week internship with EDABI data science team
- Worked on an image processing and trend detection project (Python, R, Hive)

Summer 2017 Graduate Intern, Savvysherpa Inc., Minneapolis, MN.

- o 12 week internship at a health care analytics company
- · Worked with a small team on two projects: 1. New health care member dynamic dis-enrollment prediction (R, survival analysis) and 2. FL Medicare patient-provider network analysis (R, network analysis)

Relevant Publications

Nilakanta, H., and Jones, G.L., Research Methods Foundation Project: Monte Carlo Simulation, SAGE Research Methods Foundations, edited by P. Atkinson, et al. (2020).

Nilakanta, H., Output Analysis Of Monte Carlo Methods With Applications To Networks And Functional Approximation, University of Minnesota Digital Conservancy (2020).

Nilakanta, H., Almquist, Z.W., and Jones, G.L., Ensuring Reliable Monte Carlo Estimates of Network Properties, (2019) ArXiv.

Selected Awards and Honors

Awarded by Target Corporation

- Jun 2022 Nominated by leadership to attend Target Tech Storytelling Training for leaders
- Sep 2022 Invited to represent company at 2022 Grace Hopper Conference
- Aug 2021 Invited to attend 2021 Grace Hopper Conference
- Sep 2021 Al All team meeting recognition
- Aug 2020 SPOT Award – recognition for individual performance on a team

Awarded by University of Minnesota

- Spring 2019 Bernard W. Lindgren Graduate Instructor Award, School of Statistics
- Spring 2018 Director's Award, School of Statistics
- 2017-2018 Graduate School Interdisciplinary Doctoral Fellowship
- May 2017 Social Networks and Health Fellowship, via Duke University
- Summer 2016 Lynn Lin Fellowship in Statistics, for promise in statistical consulting
- Summer 2015 First Year Graduate Research Fellowship

Service

Target Corporation

- Aug 2021 Panelist for AI Event at Grace Hopper Conference, Target Tech.
- 2020-Present Member of the Data And Inclusion (DAC) Group, Target Data Sciences.
 - Dec 2020 Data Science 4 All Mentor, Target Data Sciences with Correlation 1.

Select Affiliations and Memberships

- American Statistical Association (ASA)
- ASA Caucus for Women in Statistics (ASA CWS)
- R-Ladies Twin Cities Chapter